<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>map on Jason I. Preszler</title>
    <link>/tags/map/</link>
    <description>Recent content in map on Jason I. Preszler</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Jason Preszler</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/map/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping with an 800 Pound Gorilla</title>
      <link>/post/2019-03-18-matplotlib-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019-03-18-matplotlib-map/</guid>
      <description>I’ve been focusing on python recently to become a bi-lingual data scientist. Probably my least favorite thing about python is its plotting libraries - there are too many options built on top of matplotlib which pre-dates pandas dataframes. This makes for some clunky code and blurry boundaries (both “is that a seaborn, pandas, or matplotlib function?” and situations with 3 equally messy solutions but in very different ways). In my opinion, ggplot2’s deep interplay with dataframes makes a lot more sense and ggplot’s layers make it easy to change plot type (just switch the geom_), add facets, and tweak aesthetics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running Tacoma: Maps</title>
      <link>/post/2018-3-11-run-tacoma1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-3-11-run-tacoma1/</guid>
      <description>When I lived in Tacoma, I was running quite a bit. Since I moved away my training has become much more irregular, but I thought it would be interesting to take the Tacoma data from my current Garmin Forerunner 220 a take a look.
Data Prep The Garmin stores data in .fit format, but gpsbabel can translate to a nicely structured GPX file, which is what I’ll start with here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Idaho ACS Mapping</title>
      <link>/post/2018-01-27-acs-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-01-27-acs-map/</guid>
      <description>Recently some diversity stats have been circulated around the College of Idaho, and as new Idahoan I wondered about the general diversity (or lack thereof) in Idaho. I remembered seeing this post a while back about mapping in R, so I went to work.
Shapefiles First, we need shapefiles for both the Idaho country boundaries and census tracts, which will give finer detail for data. These can be downloaded from the [US Census Bureau] (https://www.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>